{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One of these people, who authored a manual of their grammar called the Razos, was Raimon Vidal. Another of these people is the subject of Robert Browning’s poem Sordello. William IX, Duke of Aquitaine is often called the first of these people, whose primary output consisted of cansos and sirventes and who often used the Occitan language to tell stories about chivalrous themes. For ten points, name these medieval European poets who wrote songs of courtly love.",
      "answer": "troubadours"
    },
    {
      "question": "This program was criticized for a slow reaction to the Church Rock mill disaster in 1979. This program began after schools on 93rd and 99th Street were harmed by Hooker Company’s poor management of a landfill in Niagara Falls, New York, leading numerous schoolchildren to be poisoned. Love Canal, the Valley of the Drums, and other locations are judged in the Hazard Ranking System by, for ten points, what federal program that empowers the EPA to clean up hazardous waste sites?",
      "answer": "Superfund"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city fell under the rule of the patron Ottone’s [oh-toh-nay’s] family after he won the Battle of Desio against Napo della Torre. Twelve “captains and defenders of liberty” were elected to write this city’s laws when it was briefly reorganized into the Golden Ambrosian Republic following the fall of the Visconti family. After that republic fell, this city was ruled by the Sforzas. For ten points, name this capital of Lombardy, a city in Northern Italy.",
      "answer": "Milan"
    },
    {
      "question": "An organization advocating this political ideology established its headquarters at Murphy Ranch under the leadership of William Dudley Pelley. Smedley Butler claimed that a conspiracy advocating this political ideology launched the Business Plot. The Silver Legion espoused this political ideology, sympathy for which was partially responsible for the cancellation of Father Coughlin’s radio show. For ten points, name this nationalist ideology held by American sympathizers of Germany and Italy in 1940.",
      "answer": [
        "fascism",
        "word forms, like fascist"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An opera about people working in this profession opens with a corrected quote from the Smyth Report and features the central character singing the aria “Batter my Heart, three person’d God.” Another opera titled for one of these people includes scenes entitled “Train,” “Bed,” and “Spaceship,” as well as interludes known as “knee plays” over the course of its five-hour run time. A John Adams opera set at Los Alamos depicts, for ten points, what profession depicted in Doctor Atomic and Philip Glass’s Einstein on the Beach?",
      "answer": [
        "scientists",
        "specific types of scientists, such as nuclear physicists"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this country had, in his earlier military career, led a fleet against Alfredo Acton that tried to break the Otranto Barrage. This country, which faced the 1918 Aster Revolution, was the site of a very short-lived Soviet Republic led by Bela Kun. During World War II, Miklos Horthy was a regent of, for ten points, what European country that was ruled by the medieval Arpad dynasty and, until World War I, part of a dual monarchy with Austria?",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Hungary"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the leaders of this political movement introduced the Joint Committee of Fifteen, whose members included John Bingham and chair William Fessenden. This movement, which was heavily criticized by the Dunning School, lobbied for passage of the Wade-Davis Bill and worked with “Scalawags” to expand their influence. Horace Greeley and Thaddeus Stevens led, for ten points, what faction of the Republican Party that advocated for civil rights and emancipation during Reconstruction, as opposed to more moderate politicians?",
      "answer": "Radical Republicans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man stored the remains of his long-time ally, Rwandan President Juvenal Habyarimana, at his palace in Gbadolite, this politician’s so-called “Versailles of the Jungle.” This leader deposed Patrice Lumumba and was deposed himself by Laurent Kabila in 1997. This leader changed his own name to establish pro-Africa cultural awareness and changed the name of his country to Zaire. For ten points, name this leopard print hat-wearing dictator who ruled in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.",
      "answer": "Joseph D´esir´e Mobutu or Mobutu Sese Seko Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga"
    },
    {
      "question": "The inventor of this technique worked at the Cetus Corporation and was lambasted in a 2007 New York Times article for believing in astrology, denying AIDS, and calling climate change a hoax. This technique greatly improved following the discovery of an enzyme capable of staying stable at high temperatures known as Taq [”tak”]. This technique allowed for the development of DNA testing by criminal investigators. Kary Mullis invented, for ten points, what laboratory technique that can amplify a sample of DNA?",
      "answer": "polymerase chain reaction or PCR"
    },
    {
      "question": "In May 2015, this country became the first to pass a referendum legalizing same-sex marriage, and it is considering another referendum to repeal the abortion-forbidding Article 9 of its constitution. Leo Varadkar’s elevation as leader of this country made him the first biracial leader of a European country, and the first LGBT person to hold the title of Taoiseach [tee-shuck]. For ten points, name this country where Varadkar leads Fine Gael [finn-neh GALE], the rival party to Fianna F´ail [fee-uh-nuh FOIL] and Sinn F´ein [shin FAYN] in Dublin.",
      "answer": "Republic of Ireland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The longest serving Attorney General in US history began his term under this president. William Wirt served this man, who warmed relations with Britain by starting to demilitarize the Great Lakes via the Rush-Bagot treaty. William Plumber prevented this man from becoming the second unanimously elected President. During this man’s administration, Florida was purchased by his Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams. For ten points, name this US President who limited European involvement in the Americas with his namesake doctrine.",
        "answer": "James Monroe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another of Monroe’s Cabinet members was this Treasury Secretary, who finished third in the 1824 election and was thus essentially irrelevant in the ensuing “Corrupt Bargain.”",
        "answer": "William Crawford"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The First Amendment was applied to this industry in the so-called Miracle case involving distributor Joseph Burstyn. Joseph Breen held a powerful regulatory position in this industry when it was governed by the Hays Code. Dalton Trumbo was among a group of ten people who were blacklisted from this industry by the House Un-American Activities Committee in 1947. For ten points, name this industry once heavily censored by the MPAA, which today rates its products with tags such as PG-13.",
        "answer": [
          "film industry",
          "equivalents like motion picture industry",
          "Hollywood",
          "Hollywood Ten"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hays Code weakened as films pushed its limits. In particular, this 1959 Billy Wilder comedy didn’t get Code approval due to its use of cross-dressing and risque themes, but it was a smash hit and Marilyn Monroe won a Golden Globe anyway.",
        "answer": "Some Like It Hot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One emperor of this dynasty, the Jingtai Emperor, succeeded an older brother who was captured during the Tumu Crisis. This dynasty’s rise to power was cemented at the Battle of Lake Poyang, one of the largest naval battles in history. Architectural projects undertaken during this dynasty included the Porcelain Tower of Nanjing and the fortification of the Great Wall of China. During this dynasty, the Muslim eunuch Zheng He led massive voyages throughout the Indian Ocean. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty preceded by the Mongol Yuan and succeeded by the Manchu Qing.",
        "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ming Dynasty was founded by this man, a peasant who led forces against the Yuan in the Red Turban Rebellion and established the capital at Nanjing.",
        "answer": "Hongwu Emperor or Zhu Yuanzhang"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, the nymph Arethusa surfaced from beneath the sea into a freshwater spring. This region’s city of Kamikos was ruled by the legendary Cocalus, who sheltered Daedalus after Daedalus fled from Crete. Most accounts hold that either Tartarus or this region was the final resting place of Typhon after he was vanquished by Zeus; both Typhon’s burial and the forge of Vulcan in this region were held to cause the volcanic tremors around Mount Etna. For ten points, name this island where Arethusa’s spring was found in Syracuse.",
        "answer": "Sicily"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to an ancient anecdote, this courtier to Dionysus II of Syracuse begged to switch places with his ruler for a day, but he quickly asked for his old position back when he realized the dangers of being in power.",
        "answer": [
          "Damocles",
          "Sword of Damocles"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s army inspector designed an artillery improvement in the “System of 1805” and notoriously ordered all cats to be hanged. This tsar met with Napoleon on a raft in the Neman River, where they agreed to the Treaty of Tilsit. After this man’s death, supporters of his brother started the Decembrist Revolt. Russia was brought into the Congress of Vienna by, for ten points, what tsar who was succeeded by Nicholas I after his 1825 death?",
        "answer": "Alexander I or Alexander Pavlovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Decembrist revolt opposed Nicholas I’s succession to the throne, instead supporting this older brother of Nicholas who secretly renounced the throne in 1823 to marry a Polish countess.",
        "answer": "Constantine Pavlovich"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A politician from this state had his right arm amputated without anesthesia after it was severed by a German soldier. That Medal of Honor recipient from this state served as President pro tempore of the Senate until his 2012 death, after which Brian Schatz was appointed to the Senate by this state’s governor, Neil Abercrombie. The first Asian-American woman elected to the Senate, Mazie Hirono, is also from, for ten points, what US state that, in 2017, renamed its Honolulu International Airport?",
        "answer": "Hawai’i"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Honolulu International Airport was renamed in honor of this aforementioned war hero and US Senator, who passed away in 2012. This man is the second-longest serving Senator in US history.",
        "answer": "Daniel Inouye , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location’s fall was allegedly watched by celebrating drinkers gathered on “the battery.” Inhabitants of this location under Robert Anderson were starved out by guns placed in the nearby military college, the Citadel. Sullivan’s Island, the site of nearby Fort Moultrie, was abandoned in favor of this location, which the Star of the West failed to re-supply in Charleston Harbor. For ten points, name this South Carolina fort that Confederates seized at the start of the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Fort Sumter"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort Sumter lies just off the western tip of this island at the opening to Charleston Harbor. This island, which is cut off from downtown Charleston by the Ashley River, was the site of the last armed action of the Revolutionary War in 1782.",
        "answer": "James Island"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s actions created 20,000 martyrs in his capital city of Nicomedia. This man became emperor after defeating Carinus at the Battle of the Margus. This man, who declared a price ceiling in the Edict of Maximum Prices, created a new ruling system after the Crisis of the Third Century before eventually retiring to his palace in Split to grow cabbage. The Tetrarchy was instituted by, for ten points, what Roman emperor who began the final Roman persecution of the Christians and abdicated the throne in 305 AD?",
        "answer": [
          "Diocletian",
          "Gaius Aurelius Valerius Diocletianus Augustus, but"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Diocletian’s aforementioned Edict on Maximum Prices reformed Rome’s coinage system, replacing the widespread use of this small silver coin with the argenteus, set at the value of 100 of these coins.",
        "answer": "denarius or denarii"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "John Adams Administration",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Man who won the Election of 1800 to end Adams’ presidency.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cousin of John Adams who led the Boston Tea Party, served as governor, and owned a malthouse.",
          "answer": "Samuel Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Adams supported Toussaint L’Ouverture’s revolution.",
          "answer": "Haiti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man he appointed Chief Justice in 1801 and served for 35 years.",
          "answer": "John Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for the judges, including William Marbury, that Adams appointed at the very end of his Presidency.",
          "answer": "midnight judges"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captain defended by Adams for allegedly ordering troops to fire during the Boston Massacre.",
          "answer": "Thomas Preston"
        },
        {
          "question": "1776 book, a response to Common Sense, in which Adams proposes a three-branch system with checks and balances.",
          "answer": "Thoughts on Government"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pennsylvania man who opposed the 1798 Direct House Tax and led a rebellion in Milford.",
          "answer": [
            "John Fries",
            "Fries’ Rebellion"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Spanish Civil War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Fascist generalissimo who won the war.",
          "answer": "Francisco Franco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Basque town whose 1937 bombing was depicted by Pablo Picasso.",
          "answer": "Guernica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arm of the Luftwaffe that was sent to aid the fascists.",
          "answer": "Condor Legion"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who named an International Brigade that fought in the war.",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln Brigade"
        },
        {
          "question": "North African protectorate where an uprising began the war, and where the Rif War was also fought.",
          "answer": "Spanish Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Force of sympathizers that Emile Mola claimed would help him undermine Madrid’s defenses.",
          "answer": "Fifth Column or Quinta Columna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nationalist leader of the Falange whose execution sparked great outrage during the war.",
          "answer": "Jose Antonio Primo de Rivera"
        },
        {
          "question": "River east of Madrid that was crossed by Nationalists in February 1937, though the heavy fighting failed to break the Republican lines.",
          "answer": "Battle of Jarama"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Dutch East India Company",
      "prompt": "Name the dutch east india company...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dutch capital city where it was incorporated.",
          "answer": "Amsterdam"
        },
        {
          "question": "City built by the VOC over the ruins of Jakarta in 1620, becoming the VOC’s Indonesian capital.",
          "answer": "Batavia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Form of torture, a simulation of drowning, committed by VOC men before the murders in the Amboyna Massacre.",
          "answer": "waterboarding"
        },
        {
          "question": "Southeast Asian country where the VOC traded with the Ayutthaya Kingdom.",
          "answer": [
            "Thailand",
            "Siam"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Southeast Asian country where the VOC intervened in the Trinh-Nguyen War.",
          "answer": "Vietnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where the VOC was forced out by the Koxinga [ko-shin-ga] in 1662.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Formosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Artificial island off Nagasaki from which the VOC traded with the Japanese for over 200 years.",
          "answer": "Dejima Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indonesian sultanate whose gold trade was taken by the VOC with the Painan Treaty.",
          "answer": "Aceh Sultanate"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The British branch of this movement was kickstarted by a Bryan Robertson exhibition at Whitechapel; among the works exhibited there were a collage of an advertisement for a vacuum next to a muscular man holding a (20 pts)",
        "lollipop. Another artist from this movement showed a woman thinking that she’d “rather sink than call Brad for help.” One artist who worked in this movement used silk-screening to repeatedly depict subjects like (10 pts)",
        "Chairman Mao and Marilyn Monroe. For ten points, name this artistic movement that used subjects from mass-media culture and included artists like Roy Lichtenstein and Andy Warhol."
      ],
      "answer": "Pop Art"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1961, this state’s Parchman Farm prison was the site of the detention of more than 300 Freedom Riders. This state’s Sovereignty Commission spied on the civil rights movement here and funded the legal defense of murderer Byron (20 pts)",
        "De La Beckwith. This state’s Freedom Democratic Party attempted to gain official recognition at the 1964 (10 pts)",
        "Democratic National Convention, but was rejected in favor of the all-white delegation. For ten points, name this state where Medgar Evers was murdered in 1963 in its capital of Jackson."
      ],
      "answer": "Mississippi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) To support this policy, the Duke of Richmond formed the CAPS pressure group, while Richard Cobden and John Bright co-founded a league to protest this policy in Manchester. Charles Pelham (20 pts)",
        "Villiers was the “solitary Robinson Crusoe” calling for repeal of this policy in the House of Commons. The newspaper The Economist was founded to end these laws, which Prime Minister (10 pts)",
        "Robert Peel finally repealed during the Irish Potato Famine. For ten points, name this controversial set of 19th century tariffs and high duties on the import of grains into Great Britain."
      ],
      "answer": "Corn Laws"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The buildup to this war included the assassination of Kim Ok-gyun, whose corpse was quartered and put on display as a warning, as well as a rebellion by several hundred thousand Donghak peasants. The losing side in this war lost the port city of (20 pts)",
        "Weihaiwei after most of the Beiyang Fleet was devastated at the Battle of the Yalu Rvier. The Triple Intervention by France, Germany,, and (10 pts)",
        "Russia ensured that the Liaodong Peninsula was not claimed by the winners of this war in its ending Treaty of Shimonoseki. For ten points, name this late 19th century war mostly fought in Korea, a victory for the Meiji Emperor over the Qing Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "First Sino-Japanese War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man used an automatic cumulative recorder in a self-designed chamber to take notes on subject responses to stimuli. This psychologist made the cover of Time Magazine after the publication of a book arguing against free will, (20 pts)",
        "Beyond Freedom and Dignity. The Twin Oaks Community, run by Planner-Managers, was inspired by this man’s 1948 work (10 pts)",
        "Walden Two. This man attempted to train homing pigeon bombers during World War II. For ten points, name this American behavioral psychologist and proponent of operant conditioning."
      ],
      "answer": "Burrhus Frederic “B.F.” Skinner"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The residents of four colonial towns in what is now this country, including Rufisque [roo-feesk], were granted citizenship thanks to the efforts of Blaise Diagne [dee-ahn]. The Portuguese built a slave trading outpost on (20 pts)",
        "Gor´ee Island in the harbor of what is now this country’s capital. An airport named for this country’s first president, L´eopold Senghor, lies on the narrow Cap-Vert peninsula near the (10 pts)",
        "Pointe des Alamadies, the westernmost point of the African continent. For ten points, name this Francophone African country where Macky Sall holds office in Dakar."
      ],
      "answer": "Senegal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man used Omar Khayyam’s quote “So I be written in the Book of Love” to end a seven-hour speech, usually named either “I Believe in the Law of Love” or “A Plea For Mercy,” that was given during the (20 pts)",
        "trials of Ossian Sweet’s family. This man, who represented the killers Leopold and Loeb, questioned (10 pts)",
        "William Jennings Bryan about the factual nature of the Bible during a 1925 show trial in Tennessee. For ten points, name this attorney for the defense in the Scopes Monkey Trial."
      ],
      "answer": "Clarence Darrow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this battle, the winning commander praised his officer Gisgo’s skill despite his numerical disadvantage, and regularly sent cavalry to harass enemy combatants gathering water at the Aufidus River. The winning side at this battle wisely abandoned the (20 pts)",
        "Fabian Strategy and deployed its center in a crescent formation, allowing their forces to doubly-envelop the armies led by (10 pts)",
        "Paullus and Varro. For ten points, name this 216 BC battle, a decisive victory for Hannibal during the Second Punic War, that followed his victories at Lake Trasimene and Trebia."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Cannae"
    }
  ]
}